<chapter>
 <title>Getting Started</title>
 <sect1 id="ch03-Starting">
  <title>Starting Loggerithim</title>
  <para>
   Loggerithim has two parts that must be started, the loggerserver and the
   web interface.  The loggerserver was installed during the automated install,
   and it should have an init.d script that will automatically start it at
   boot time.  To start the loggerserver, use this command:
  </para>
<systemitem class="prompt">#</systemitem> <userinput>/etc/init.d/loggerserver start</userinput>
  <para>
   The web interface can be started by simply starting apache.  I will assume
   you know how to do this already.
  </para>
  <para>
   With the loggerserver running, your agents should be able to send metrics.
   The loggerserver logs to syslog, so consult your systems syslog files to
   see if metrics are coming in.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="ch03-SomeBasics">
  <title>Some Basics</title>
  <para>
   If you visit the URL you've setup for Loggerithim, you should see a login
   screen.  If you have not logged in yet, do so now.
  </para>
  <para>
   You should be greeted by a relatively sparse web page.  This is normal,
   because Loggerithim doesn't have any information about your hosts yet.
   Before we start adding departments, systems, and hosts it is important
   that we take a look at each of these entities and make sure we understand
   them.
  </para>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Hosts</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
   <emphasis>Hosts</emphasis> are entities that Loggerithim monitors.
   These can be machines that are running the loggeragent daemon, or devices
   that are monitored via Smeeplets.
  </para>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Systems</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
   <emphasis>Systems</emphasis> are an organizational unit used to group
   Hosts.  For example, say you have an application composed of a database
   server and application server called WidgetMaker.  You would create a 
   System called WidgetMaker and make your database and application server
   a part of it.
  </para>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Metrics</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
   <emphasis>Metrics</emphasis> are counters or values gathered from Hosts.
   Generally, this term is used to represent a pile of values sent as one
   big message.
  </para>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Departments</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
   <emphasis>Departments</emphasis> are organizational units that hold
   systems.  Using our WidgetMaker example again, you might have both a
   Development and Production department for WidgetMaker.
  </para>
  <para>
   Departments and systems have no actual relationship, they are simply
   tied to the Host.  To setup your WidgetMaker environment you would
   create a Production and Development department, a WidgetMaker system,
   and select the appropriate values in the dropboxes for adding a host.
  </para>
  <para>
   Now that we understand departments and systems, feel free to go
   to the Admin section and add some departments and systems. Use the
   'Add A System' and 'Add a Department' links.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="ch03-SpeakingOfHosts">
  <title>Speaking Of Hosts...</title>
  <para>
   Now that we have covered Departments and Systems, we can work with
   hosts.  To monitor a machine's metrics, you need to have installed
   and started the loggeragent, as described in Chapter 2, 
   <emphasis>Installing the loggeragent.</emphasis>.
  </para>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Hosts</primary>
   <secondary>adding</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
   Next, add the Host to Loggerithim through the Admin section.  The
   important fields are Hostname, IP, Active, and Purpose.  When a host connects
   to pass in some metrics, the loggerserver tries to find the host by IP
   address.  This means that you need to have the IP match the address that
   the host will be sending metrics through.  If that fails, the loggerserver
   will try to find a host with a hostname that matches the hostname provided in
   the metric.  If a Host has more than one hostname, use the hostname that
   the box gives when you execute the <command>hostname</command> command.
   The Active box is a flag used to determine if the box should be displayed in
   Loggerithim's menu.  If Active is not checked, the box will not be displayed.
  </para>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Host</primary>
   <secondary>purpose</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
   The Purpose field is an explanation of the box's responsibilities.
   You can use 'SMTP Server', rather than trying to decipher whatever
   silly naming scheme your manager is forcing on you.
  </para>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Profile</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
   The Profile field determines what Attributes a host has.  For example, if
   you choose the canned Profile 'Linux' for a Host, then all the Attributes
   for Linux will be added to that Host.  For example, if you have a pile of
   Cisco routers that you want to monitor, you could define a Profile that
   defines a set of metrics that you want to use with them.  Then, when you add
   them to Loggerithim, you can simply choose the 'Cisco' Profile you created
   rather than having to add a ton of Attributes to the Host.
  </para>
  <para>
   Changing a Profile after you've used it to add Hosts does NOT change the
   Attributes of existing Hosts.  It is only used as a guide when the Hosts are
   added.  The existing profiles should suit your needs for now, we will cover
   creating new profiles later.
  </para>
  <para>
   Be sure to choose a system and department, which you added in the last
   section.  The Database information can be ignored for now, it is used
   when extending Loggerithim.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="ch03-Results">
  <title>Results</title>
  <para>
   If you installed, configured, and started the loggeragent and also added
   a host representing that box into Loggerithim, data should start
   collecting.  Don't be worried if you click one of the links and don't
   get any pretty results.  It takes a few samples for Loggerithim to get a box
   figured out.  Some metrics, like CPU and network traffic, require three 
   readings to calculate their values.  Continue adding Hosts to your setup
   until you've added all the Hosts you want to monitor.
  </para>
  <para>
   When you do see your first graph with real data, it should be fairly simple
   to read.  The dropbox can be changed to graph a different number of hours,
   days, weeks, or months. 
  </para>
  <para>
   If you see a vertical red line on the graph, this signifies midnight.  This
   should help you orient yourself when you are looking at a graph.
  </para>
  <para>
   The dashed lines and the numbers drawn in the right hand margin signify the
   average for a particular line.
  </para>
  <para>
   Don't forget that the loggerserver logs it's actions to syslog.  You can
   tail your messages file to watch any errors that might show up.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="ch03-Preferences">
  <title>Preferences</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>User</primary>
    <secondary>preferences</secondary>
   </indexterm>
  <para>
   The user preferences are as follows:
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis>Password</emphasis> - Self-explanatory, I hope.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis>Department &amp; System</emphasis> - When you visit Loggerithim,
   it will show you the Department and System of your choice.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis>Color</emphasis> - If enabled, Loggerithim will color code
   some of the key metrics for a Hosts on the main page.  This allows you to
   glance at a System and see it's state.  This can be expensive if you
   monitor alot of Hosts, so it's configurable.
  </para>
  <para>
   With what we've covered so far, it is pretty easy to keep an eye on your
   boxes.  In the next chapter we'll dig deeper and learn about Loggerithim's
   more advanced capabilites.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
