<preface>
 <title>Preface</title>
 <simplesect>
  <para>
   Time travel has long been the stuff of science fiction.  For as long as people
   have been able to break things, the ability to manipulate time has been on
   their minds.  Stories, books, and even movies have repeatedly visited this
   subject.
  </para>
  <para>
   Managing the various devices involved in our IT infrastructures could certainly
   benefit from the use of time travel.  The ability to go back and see what
   caused an outage, or how things ran before the last patch would be useful.
  </para>
  <para>
   For as long as people have had to perform labor, they have desired to offload
   it onto others.  Computers have helped us in this, usually generating more
   work than they save, but that is a different story all together.
  </para>
  <para>
   Having a robot that can intelligently do your bidding (well, within reason)
   would also be beneficial.  A robot that can speak to your computers and
   give them orders might come in handy.
  </para>
  <para>
   Simply put, Loggerithim aims to be your time machine and robot, allowing you
   to go back some amount of time and see how things were.  While we are at it,
   we'll also use this flow of information to check for problems.  We will have
   the opportunity to give the machine some instructions if there are problems,
   or maybe use that same ability to detect problems before they happen.
  </para>
 </simplesect>
 <sect1 id="preface-PlatformNotes">
  <title>Platform Notes</title>
  <para>
   Loggerithim is developed on RedHat Linux 7.2 for x86, Solaris 6 for Sparc,
   Solaris 8 for Sparc, and MacOS X Jaguar (10.2).  Perl 5.8.0, Apache 1.3.26,
   mod_perl 1.28, and PostgreSQL 7.3.4 round out the major software portions.
   Testing is done on RedHat Linux 9.0 as well.
  </para>
  <para>
   All the components of Loggerithim are written to be portabile across
   UNIX boxen to the best of the author's understanding, which may be lacking
   on many platforms.  Still, all the pieces <emphasis>should</emphasis> play
   well together on any OS where Perl and C work properly.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="preface-ContactInformation">
  <title>Contact Information</title>
  <para>
   This documentation is a living entity.  It's contents are probably littered
   with misspellings and grammatical errors.  Maybe some of the instructions
   are wrong.  Please communicate any errors you find or suggestions you have
   to the mailing list at <email>loggerithim-users@lists.sourceforge.net</email>
   or directly to the author at <email>gphat@loggerithim.org</email>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="preface-GettingHelp">
  <title>Getting Help</title>
  <para>
   Loggerithim can be a complicated beast.  If you need help, visit the web
   page at http://www.loggerithim.org.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="preface-Acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgments</title>
  <para>
   Despite the fact that you currently only see a single name on the
   documentation and source code of Loggerithim, quite a few people have had
   a hand in making it work.  Most notably is my employer, InPHact.  The
   management there has been kind enough to allow me to release my project to
   the public under an Open Source License.  Specific thanks go to Helen, Rick,
   and Howard for being understanding managers and helpful critics.  Thanks to
   Canton for incessant proofreadings and long shpleels about how this or that
   worked.  Also to Mike for constantly telling me that pieces were not good
   enough (not that he has stopped yet), and Kevin for inspiring my early
   mod_perl adventures.  Finally, my lovely wife Jennifer for pretending to care
   when I show her the new whiz-bang feature I cooked up.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</preface>
